Hey, everyone.
Welcome to the first and
introductory lecture for CS 25,
Transformers United.
So CS 25 was a class
that the three of us
created and taught at
Stanford in the fall of 2021,
and the subject of
the class is not
as the picture might suggest.
It's not about robots that
can transform into cars.
It's about deep learning
models and specifically
a particular kind of
deep learning models
that have revolutionized
multiple fields,
starting from natural
language processing
to things like computer
vision and reinforcement
learning to name a few.
We have an exciting set of
videos lined up for you.
We had some truly
fantastic speakers
come and give talks about how
they were applying Transformers
in their own research.
And we hope you will enjoy
and learn from these talks.
This video is purely
an introductory lecture
to talk a little bit
about transformers.
And before we get
started, I'd like
to introduce the instructors.
So my name is Advay.
I am a software
engineer at a company
called Applied Intuition.
Before this, I was a master's
student in CS at Stanford.
And I am one of the
co-instructors for CS25.
Chetanya, Div, if the two of
you could introduce yourselves.
So hi, everyone.
I am a PhD student at Stanford.
Before this, I was
pursuing a master's here,
researching a lot in generative
modeling, reinforcement
learning, and robotics.
So nice to meet you all.
Yeah, that was Div, since
he didn't say his name.
Chetanya, if you want
to introduce yourself.
Yeah.
Hi, everyone.
My name is Chetanya,
and I'm currently
working as an ML engineer at
a start-up called Moveworks.
Before that, I was
a master's student
at Stanford specializing
in NLP and was
a member of the
prize-winning Stanford's team
for the Alexa Prize Challenge.
All right, awesome.
So moving on to the
rest of this talk,
essentially, what we
hope you will learn
watching these
videos and what we
hope the people who took our
class in the fall of 2021
learned is three things.
One is we hope you will
have an understanding of how
Transformers work.
Secondly, we hope you will learn
and, by the end of these talks,
understand how Transformers
are being applied beyond just
natural language processing.
And thirdly, we hope
that some of these talks
will spark some new
ideas within you
and hopefully lead to new
directions of research,
new kinds of innovation,
and things of that sort.
And to begin, we're going
to talk a little bit
about Transformers
and introduce some
of the context behind
transformers as well.
And for that, I'd like
to hand it off to Div.
So hi, everyone.
So welcome to our
Transformer seminar.
So let's start first with
an overview of the attention
timeline and how it came to be.
The key idea about Transformers
was the simple attention
mechanism that was
developed in 2017.
And this all started
with this one paper
called "Attention is All
you Need," by Vaswani et al.
Before 2017, we used to have
this prehistoric era where
we had older models like RNNs,
LSTMs, and simpler attention
mechanisms
And eventually, the
growth in Transformers
has exploded into other fields
and has become prominent
in all of machine learning.
And I'll go and see and
show how this has been used.
So in the prehistoric era,
there used to be RNNs.
There were different models like
the Sequence2Sequence, LSTMs,
GRUs.
They were good at encoding
some sort of memory,
but they did not work for
encoding long sequences.
And they were very bad
at encoding context.
So here is an example.
If you have a sentence like
I grew up in France dot,
dot, dot, so I
speak fluent- then
you want to fill this with
French based on the context,
but like a LSTM model might not
know what it is and might just
make a very big mistake here.
Similarly, we can show some
sort of correlation map
here, where if you
have a pronoun like it,
we want it to correlate
to one of the past nouns
that we have seen
so far, like animal.
But again, older models
were really not good
at this context encoding.
So where we are currently now
is on the verge of take-off.
We began to realize the
potential of Transformers
in different fields.
We have started to use
them to solve long sequence
problems in protein folding,
such as the AlphaFold
model from DeepMind,
which gets 95% accuracy
on different challenges,
and offline RL.
We can use it for few-shot
and zero-shot generalization,
for text and image generation.
And we can also use
for content generation.
So here's an
example from OpenAI,
where you can give a
different text prompt
and have an AI generate a
fictional image for you.
And so there's a doc on
this that you can also
watch on YouTube,
which basically
says that LSTMs are dead,
and long live Transformers.
So what's the future?
So we can enable a lot more
applications for Transformers.
They can be applied to any
form of sequence modeling.
So we could use them
for video understanding.
We can use them for
finance and a lot more.
So basically, imagine all
sorts of generative modeling
problems.
Nevertheless, there are a
lot of missing ingredients.
So like the human
brain, we need some sort
of external memory unit, which
is the hippocampus for us.
And there are some
early works here.
So one nice work you
might want to check out
is called Neural
Turing Machines.
Similarly, the current
attention mechanisms
are very computationally
complex in terms
of time and correlating
which we will discuss later.
And we want to make
them more linear.
And the third problem
is that we want
to align our current
sort of language models
with how the human brain
works and human values.
And this is also a big issue.
OK.
So now I will deep dive--
I will dive deeper into
the attention mechanisms
and show how they
came out to be.
So initially, they used to
be very simple mechanisms.
Attention was inspired by
the process of importance
weighting, of putting attention
on different parts of an image
like similar to a human,
where you might focus more
on a foreground if you have
an image of a dog compared
to the rest of the background.
So in the case of soft
attention, what you do is
you learn the simple
soft attention weighting
for each pixel, which can
be a weight between 0 to 1.
The problem over
here is that this is
a very expensive computation.
And you can show--
as is shown in the
figure on the left,
you can see we are
calculating this attention
map for the whole image.
What you can do instead is
you can just get a 0 to 1
attention map, where we directly
put a 1 on wherever the dog is
and 0 wherever
it's a background.
This is like less
computationally expensive,
but the problem is it's
non-differentiable and makes
things harder to train.
Going forward, we also
have different varieties
of basic attention
mechanisms that were
proposed before self-attention.
So the first term right here
is global attention models.
So global attention model
is for each hidden layer
input-- hidden layer output.
You learn attention
weight of a of p
and this is
elementwise multiplied
with your current output to
get your final output, yt.
Similarly, you have the
local attention models,
where instead of calculating
the global attention
for over the whole
sequence length,
you only calculate the
attention over a small window.
And then you weight by the
attention of the window
into the current output to
get the final output you need.
So moving on, I will
pass on to Chetanya
to discuss self-attention
mechanisms and platforms.
Thank you, Div, for covering
a brief overview of how
the primitive versions
of attention work.
Now just before we talk about
self-attention, just a bit
of trivia, that term was
first introduced by a paper
from Lin et al., which
provided a framework
for a self-attentive mechanism
for sentence and meanings.
And now moving on to the
main crux of the Transformers
paper, which was the
self-attention block.
So self-attention is the
basis, is the main building
block for what makes a
Transformers model work so well
and to enable them and
make them so powerful.
So to think of it
more easily, we
can break down
the self-attention
as a search retrieval problem.
So the problem is that
given a query, q, and v,
we need to find
a set of keys, k,
which are most similar
to q and return
the corresponding key
values called v. Now
these three vectors can be
drawn from the same source.
For example, we can
have that q, k, and v
are all equal to a single
vector x, where x can
be output of a previous layer.
In Transformers,
these vectors are
obtained by applying different
linear transformations to x.
So as to enable the
model to capture
more complex interactions
between the different tokens
at different places
of the sentence.
Now how attention is computed
is just a weighted summation
of the similarities between
the query and key vectors,
which is weighted by
the respective value
for those keys.
And in the Transformers
paper, they
used the scaled dot-product
as a similarity function
for the queries and keys.
And another important
aspect of the Transformers
was the introduction of
Multi-head self-attention.
So what Multi-head
Self-attention means
is that the self-attention
is for at every layer
the self-attention is
performed multiple times,
which enables the model to
learn multiple representations
of spaces.
So in a way, you can think of
it that each head has a power
to look at different things and
to learn different semantics.
For example, one
head can be learning
to try to predict what
is the part of speech
for those tokens.
One head might be learning
what is the syntactic structure
of the sentence and
all those things
that are there to
understand what the upcoming
sentence means.
Now to better understand
what the self-attention works
and what are the
different computations,
there is a short video.
So in this-- so as
you can see, there
are three incoming tokens,
so input 1, input 2, input 3.
We apply linear transformations
to get the key value vectors
for each input and then
give-- once a query, q, comes,
we calculate its similarity
with the respective key vectors
and then multiply those
scores with the value vector.
And then add them all
up to get the output.
The same computation is then
performed on all the tokens.
And we get the output of
the self-attention layer.
So as you can see
here, the final output
of self-attention layer
is in dark green that's
at the top of the screen.
So now again, for
the final token,
we perform everything same,
queries multiplied by keys.
We get the similarity scores.
And then those similarity
scores weigh the value vectors.
And then we finally
perform the addition
to get the self-attention output
of the Transformers block.
Apart from
self-attention, there are
some other necessary
ingredients that makes
the Transformers so powerful.
One important aspect
is the presence
of positional representations
or the embedding layer.
So the way RNNs
worked very well was
that since they process
each of the information
in a sequential ordering.
So there was this notion
of ordering, right,
which is also very important
in understanding language
because we all know that
we read any piece of text
from left to right in
most of the languages
and also right to left
in some languages.
So there is a notion
of ordering which
is lost in kind
of self-attention
because every word is
attending to every other word.
That's why this paper
introduced a separate embedding
layer for introducing
positional representations.
The second important aspect
is having nonlinearities.
So if you think of all
the computation that
is happening in the
self-attention layer,
it's all linear because it's
all matrix multiplication.
But as we all know, that
deep learning models
work well when
they are able to--
when they are able to learn more
complex mappings between input
and output, which can be
attained by a simple MLP.
And the third important
component of the self--
of the Transformers
is the masking.
So masking is what allows to
parallelize the operations.
Since every word can
attend to every other word,
in the decoder part
of our transformers,
which Advay is going to
be talking about later,
is the problem becomes that
you don't want the decoder
to look into the
future because that
can result in data leakage.
So that's why masking
helps the decoder
to avoid that future information
and learn only what has been--
what the model has
processed so far.
So now onto the
encoder-decoder architecture
of the Transformers.
Advay.
Yeah.
Thanks, Chetanya, for
talking about self-attention.
So self-attention is sort
of the key ingredient or one
of the key ingredients
that allows Transformers
to work so well, but
at a very high level,
the model that was proposed
in the Vaswani et al.
paper of 2017 was like previous
language models in the sense
that it had an
encoder-decoder architecture.
What that means is--
let's say you're working
on a translation problem.
You want to translate
English to French.
The way that would
work is you would
read in the entire input
of your English sentence.
You would encode that input.
So that's the encoded
part of the network.
And then you would
generate token
by token the corresponding
French translation.
And the decoder is the
part of the network
that is responsible for
generating those tokens.
So you can think of these
encoder blocks and decoder
blocks as essentially
something like LEGO.
They have these subcomponents
that make them up.
And in particular,
the encoder block
has three main subcomponents.
The first is the
self-attention layer
that Chetanya talked
about earlier.
And, as talked about
earlier as well,
you need a feed-forward
layer after that
because the
self-attention layer only
performs linear operations.
And so you need something that
can capture the nonlinearities.
You also have a layer
norm after this.
And lastly, there are
residual connections
between different
encoder blocks.
The decoder is very
similar to the encoder,
but there's one
difference, which
is that it has this extra layer,
because the decoder doesn't
just do Multi-head
Attention on the output
of the previous layers.
So for context, the encoder
does Multi-head Attention
for each self-attention
layer in the encoder block.
And each of the encoder blocks
does Multi-head Attention
looking at the previous
layers of the encoder blocks.
The decoder, however,
does that in the sense
that it also looks at the
previous layers of the decoder,
but it also looks at the
output of the encoder.
And so it needs a
Multi-head Attention layer
over the encoder blocks.
And lastly, there's
masking as well.
So if you are--
because every token can
look at every other
token, you want
to sort of make
sure in the decoder
that you're not looking
into the future.
So if you're in position
3, for instance,
you shouldn't be able to look
at position 4 and position 5.
So those are sort of
all the components
that led to the creation of
the model in the Vaswani et al.
paper.
And let's talk a little
bit about the advantages
and drawbacks of this model.
So the two main advantages which
are huge advantages and which
are why Transformers
have done such a good job
of revolutionizing many, many
fields within deep learning
are as follows.
So the first is there
is this constant path
length between any two
positions in a sequence
because every token
in the sequence
is looking at every other token.
And this basically
solves the problem
that they've talked about
earlier with long sequences.
You don't have this
problem with long sequences
where if you're trying
to predict a token
that depends on a word that was
far, far behind in a sentence.
You don't have the problem
of losing that context.
Now the distance
between them is only one
in terms of the path length.
Also, because of the nature
of the computation that's
happening, Transformer
models lend themselves really
well to parallelization
and because
of the advances that
we've had with GPUs.
Basically, if you take
a Transformer model
with n parameters and you take a
model that isn't a Transformer,
say, like an LSTM also
with n parameters,
training the
Transformer model is
going to be much faster
because of the parallelization
that it leverages.
So those are the advantages.
The disadvantages are
basically self-attention takes
quadratic time because
every token looks
at every other token.
Order n squared as you
might know does not scale,
and there's actually
been a lot of work
in trying to tackle this.
So we've linked to some here.
Big Bird, Linformer,
and Reformer
are all approaches to try and
make this linear or quasilinear
essentially.
And yeah, we highly
recommend to--
recommend going through
Jay Alammar's blog,
"The Illustrated
Transformer." which
provides great visualizations
and explains everything
that we just talked
about in great detail.
Yeah.
And I'd like to pass it on
to Chetanya for applications
of Transformers.
Yeah.
So now moving on to some
of the recent work--
some of the work that
very shortly followed
the Transformers paper.
So one of the
models that came out
was GPT, the GPT architecture,
which was released by OpenAI.
So OpenAI had the latest model
that OpenAI has and the GPT
series and the GPT-3.
So it consists of
only the decoder
blocks from Transformers.
And it's trained on a
traditional language modeling
task, which is predicting
the current token-- which
is creating the next token
given the last t tokens
that the model has seen.
And for any downstream
tasks, now the model
can just-- you can just
train a classification layer
on the last hidden state, which
can have any number of labels.
And since the model is
generative in nature,
you can also use the
pretrained network
for generative kind of
tasks, such as summarization
and natural language
generation for that instance.
Another important aspect
that GPT gained popularity
was its ability to
be able to perform
in-context learning,
what the authors called
in-context learning.
So this is the ability
wherein the model can
learn under few-shot
settings, what
the task is to complete
the task without performing
any gradient updates.
For example, let's
say, the model
has shown a bunch of
addition examples.
And then if you pass in a
new input and leave the--
and just leave it
at equal to sign,
the model tries to predict
the next token, which
very well comes out to be
the sum of the numbers that
is shown.
Another example can be
also the spell correction
task or the translation task.
So this was the ability that
made GPT-3 so much talked about
in the NLP world.
And right now also,
many applications
have been made using GPT-3
which includes one of them being
the VS Code Copilot, which tries
to generate a piece of code
given docstring kind of
natural language text.
Another major
model that came out
that was based on the
Transformers' architecture
was BERT.
So BERT lends its
name from-- it's
an acronym for Bidirectional
Encoder Representations
from Transformers.
It consists of only the encoder
blocks of the Transformers,
which is unlike GPT-3, which
had only the decoder blocks.
Because of this change,
there comes a problem
because BERT has only
the encoder block.
So it sees the
entire piece of text.
It cannot be pretrained on a
naive language modeling task
because of the problem of
data leakage from the future.
So what the authors came
up with was a clever idea.
And they came up with a novel
task called Masked Language
Modeling, which included
to replace certain words
with a placeholder.
And then the model tries to
predict those words given
the entire context.
Now, apart from this
token-level task,
the authors also added
a second objective
called the Next Sentence
Prediction, which
was a sentence-level
task, wherein
given two chunks of text,
the model tried to predict
whether the second sentence
followed the other sentence
or not, followed the
first sentence or not.
And now after pretraining this
model for any downstream tasks,
the model can be
further fine-tuned
with an additional
classification layer
just like it was in GPT-3.
So these are the two models
that have been very popular
and have made a lot of
applications, made their way
in a lot of applications.
But the landscape has
changed quite a lot
since we have taken this class.
There are models with
different computing techniques
like ELECTRA, DeBERTa.
And there are also
models that do
well in like other
modalities and which
we are going to be talking
about in other lecture series
as well.
So yeah, that's all
from this lecture.
And thank you for tuning in.
Yeah.
Just want to end by
saying, thank you
all for watching this.
And we have a
really exciting set
of videos with truly
amazing speakers.
And we hope you are able
to derive value from that.
Sure.
Thanks a lot.
Thank you.
Thank you, everyone.